Works again.
又起作用了。
Okay, so the plan for today is talking about GFS,
好的，今天的计划是关于 GFS ，
I'm gonna do it in sort of multiple steps.
我会分多个步骤来做。
One I'm gonna talk a little bit about storage in general,
首先，我会从总体上谈一下存储，
and why it's so important,
为什么它如此重要，
and why we spend a lot of time
以及为什么我们花很多时间
in this class talking about it.
在这堂课上讨论它。
Then I'm going to talk a little bit about
然后我将讨论一下，
in terms of GFS and it's main design,
从 GFS 的角度，以及它的主要设计，
we'll focus on consistency,
我们重点关注一致性，
which will be the main theme through this lecture,
它是这堂课的主要主题，
as part of the consistency,
作为一致性的一部分，
you know we probably I do,
我们很可能这样，
hopefully there's still time to breakout of the room,
希望还有时间进入分组会议室，
and talk a little bit about the breakout rooms about the lecture,
讨论一下，分组会议关于课程，
or the question was posed for lecture,
或者课程贴出的问题，
and we'll resume discussion of of consistency.
我们将继续讨论一致性的问题。
Okay, so,
好的，所以，
let me talk a little bit about storage systems in general,
让我来总体上地讨论一下存储系统，
and why they so feature so prominently in 6.824,
以及为什么它们在 6.824 中占据重要地位，
and the main reason is,
主要原因是，
it's just a fantastic building block,
它是一个神奇的构建组件，
for fault tolerance systems.
用于容错系统。
And so the basic idea is that,
所以基本的想法是，
if you if you can build an durable storage system,
如果你能建立一个持久的存储系统，
then you can structure sort of your application as
然后你可以构建你的应用程序，
you know the app is basically you know state less,
应用程序无状态的，
and then the storage holds all the persistent state.
然后存储保存所有的持久状态。
And that simplifies the design of the app tremendously,
这极大地简化了应用程序的设计，
because the app basically you know doesn't really have any stable storage,
因为应用程序没有任何持久的存储空间，
you know that it has to maintain itself,
它必须保持自己，
in fact is a fact that all out to storage system,
事实上，这些都在存储系统，
so you can start up a new application very quickly,
所以，你可以非常快速地启动新的应用程序，
you know it crash doesn't really matter,
它崩溃并不重要，
because it only has soft state, not any hard state,
因为它只有软状态，没有任何硬状态，
and then start up again,
然后再重新启动，
when you start up again,
当你重新启动时，
you just reach state from the distributed storage system.
你就从分布式存储系统进入状态。
And you can see this quick look at any website,
你可以在任何网站上看到这个，
you know basically structured in that way,
基本上就是这样构建的，
there's a storage backend, you know that maintains state,
有一个存储后端，用来保持状态，
and then there's the application,
然后是应用程序，
middle tier that does the application specific computation,
参与应用程序计算的中间层，
or whatever runs Javascript Go or whatever,
或者运行 Javascript Go 的程序，
and you know it front ends that out
它的前端在，
you know to a client on the Internet.
在互联网上的客户端。
And, so storage just like this fantastic building block,
所以，存储像一个神奇的构建组件,
and I think this is one reason,
我想这是一个原因，
that we're going to see this over and over in this class.
为什么我们会在这节课上反复看到这个。
That means that you know the storage system itself,
这意味着存储系统本身，
of course has to be highly fault tolerant,
当然必须具有高度的容错性，
and as it turns out to be a very tricky thing to do,
这是一件非常棘手的事情，
and so that is the other side,
这就是另一个方面，
the flip side of it,
另一方面，
it will make life of the application easy,
它使应用程序的生命周期变得简单，
but you know the designing actually fault tolerant storage system is not easy.
但是设计容错存储系统并不容易。
So why is it hard,
那么为什么这么难，
and basically come down to you know one reason,
可以归结为一个原因，
that drives these designs,
驱动这些设计，
which is like we generally want high performance,
我们通常希望获得高性能，
when you think about the storage system for today,
当你考虑今天的存储系统，
you know GFS its main goal is
GFS 的主要目标是，
to basically support mapreduce types applications,
支持 mapreduce 类型的应用程序，
and so, it really needs high performance.
所以，它需要高性能。
Well, what does that mean,
好的，那是什么意思，
well, it means that you typically have to shard data across servers,
这意味着你必须跨服务器对数据分片，
so you cant't use one server,
所以你不能使用一台服务器，
you have to use multiple servers,
你必须使用多台服务器，
and the reason you want to read from the disk,
你想要从磁盘中读取的原因，
and often particular machine has limited throughput,
通常特定的机器具有有限的吞吐量，
if you want to read more
如果你想读取更多，
than actually a single disk can sustain,
超过一个磁盘的容量，
you have to use multiple disks,
你必须使用多个磁盘，
and you have to use multiple network cards,
你必须使用多个网卡，
and so you can immediately get into these sort of large scale systems
你可以立即进入这种大规模系统，
in the GFS where you have thousands of machines.
在 GFS 中，有数千台机器。
But if you have many servers,
但是如果你有多台服务器，
some are gonna fail,
有些会失败，
you gonna get failures,
你会遭遇失败，
or you can maybe,
或者你可能，
you can see more exclusively constant faults,
你会看到更多专有的不断的故障，
and you know let's say the computer crashes, you know once a year,
假设电脑崩溃，一年一次，
you know, now let's say you know you have thousands of machines,
现在假设你有数千台机器，
like in the GFS paper,
就像在 GFS 的论文中，
so many more in the thousand machines,
比上千台机器更多，
at minimal thousand machines,
最少一千台机器，
how many failures are going to see per day, roughly.
粗略地说，每天会看到多少次失败。
Around 3.
大概 3 次。
Yeah, around 3, right,
是的，大约 3 次，
that means that you know sort of a failure of a computer
这意味着计算机的失败，
like my laptop at the beginning of the lecture,
像我在课程开头的笔记本电脑，
is just a common scenario,
是一个常见的场景，
and so if you're going to move up to
如果你上升到
more than a thousand, ten thousand machines, a hundred thousand machines,
超过一千台，一万台机器，十万台机器，十万台机器，
you're running applications using that kind of number of computers,
你使用这种数量的计算机运行应用程序，
you're gonna get faults,
你会遇到失败，
and so that means you want a fall tolerance design.
这意味着你需要一个容错的设计。
And you know to get fault tolerance,
为了获得容错能力，
you know at least in the case,
至少在这种情况下，
where storage system with the typical approach the way to go,
存储系统采用的传统方法，
we're gonna go with replication,
我们将使用复制，
copy data on multiple disks,
复制数据到多个磁盘上，
you know so that they what this fails,
这样，当这个失败时，
you know the other disk hopefully have the data.
希望另一个磁盘有数据。
But if you go into replication
但是如果你使用复制，
and so the data is in multiple places,
数据位于多个位置，
that runs into the challenge that the data may be out of sync,
就会遇到数据不同步的挑战，
and so you actually get into inconsistent potential inconsistencies.
你会陷入可能的不一致。
You know, to avoid these inconsistencies,
为了避免这些不一致，
you know if you desire a strong consistency,
如果你想要强一致性，
basically your replicate system behaves as if it's,
你的复制系统的行为就像
it as the same behavior as an unreplicated system.
就像未复制系统的行为。
Then you will need some persistency protocol,
然后，你将需要一些持久性协议，
and that's gonna require some maybe sending messages
这可能需要发送一些消息，
and may be lower performance,
而且可能会降低性能，
maybe the messages themselves, not really huge performance overhead,
也许消息本身并不会带来很大的性能开销，
but you know [] knowledge we'll see,
但是我们会看到的[]知识，
and you might actually have to read or write to durable storage,
你可能必须读取或写入持久存储，
as part of that protocol
作为协议的一部分，
and you know reading or writing to storage
而且读取或写入存储
intentionally tends to be quite expensive.
往往是相当昂贵的。
So here we see this conundrum,
所以我们在这里看到了这个难题，
like you know we want high performance,
我们想要高性能，
we want fault tolerance,
我们想要容错，
because we have many servers,
因为我们有很多服务器，
we want high performance over many servers,
我们希望在多台服务器上实现高性能，
many servers means fault tolerance,
许多服务器意味着容错，
that means application that means you know inconsistencies,
这意味着应用程序不一致的情况，
because we have data in multiple places,
因为我们在多个地方都有数据，
to fix the inconsistencies,
为了修复不一致，
we need to get a protocol that might lower performance.
我们需要一个协议，可能会降低性能。
So here sort of this fundamental challenge
所以，这是基本挑战，
in designing these distributed storage systems,
在设计这些分布式存储系统时，
that user struggle between consistency and performance,
用户在一致性和性能之间苦苦挣扎，
and we'll see that throughout the term.
我们将在整个学期中看到这一点。
So let me talk a little bit about consistency,
所以，让我来讨论一下一致性，
and sort of a very high level,
从很高的层面,
and I promise you for the rest of this semester,
我向你保证在这学期剩下的时间里，
we're going more detail as we go.
我们将会有更多的详细介绍。
So first let's talk again about the ideal consistency,
首先，让我们讨论一下理想的一致性，
an ideal consistency, the way the simplest way to think about is that,
理想的一致性最简单的思考方式是，
basically the machine behaves as if it's a single system,
机器的行为就像一个单一系统一样，
that's also the desired behavior,
这也是我们想要的行为，
and the sort of two things that make the desired behavior
有两件事产生想要的行为，
or two hazards that make this design behavior hard to achieve,
或两种危险使得这种设计行为很难实现，
or you know at least you know requires some thinking,
或者至少需要一些思考，
and one is concurrency and second thing is failures.
第一个是并发性，第二个是失败。
So let me start with consumer concurrency,
让我从消费者并发性开始，
because even if you have a single machine with multiple clients,
因为即使你有一台具有多个客户端的计算机，
so your concurrency within a single machine,
你在一台计算机中的并发性，
you actually have to think about consistency,
你也必须考虑一致性，
and this cause is quite obvious.
这个原因是很明显的。
Let's say we have one machine, one disk,
假设我们有一台机器，一个磁盘，
both of requests you know come in from different clients,
有两个请求来自不同的客户端，
and if the machine is a multi-processor machine,
如果机器是多处理器机器，
they might actually run these requests internally in parallel.
它们可能会在内部并行运行这些请求。
So, so let's think a little bit about it,
所以，让我们稍微想一想，
what does it mean,
这是什么意思，
so so let's say we have client 1,
所以，假设我们有客户端 1 ，
that does a write operation to key x and write 1,
它对键 x 写入 1 ，
and at the same time,
与此同时，
there's a request coming in with writes to x too,
也有一个请求对 x 写入，
but actually writes the value 2, right.
但写入的值是 2 。
Now, you know if you want to specify or stage what consistency means,
现在，如果你想具体说明或展示一致性是什么，
we need some rule about like what will happen,
我们需要一些规则，比如会发生什么，
in the rules typically phrased from the perspective of the reader,
在这个规则中，通常从读者的角度表述，
so let's say there's another reader coming in,
假设有另一个读取者进来，
where another request coming in from another client and actually read x,
来自另一个客户端的另一个请求，并读取 x ，
the question is,
问题是，
what is the value that actually that reader or that client observes.
读者或客户端观察到的值是什么。
And look a little bit more complicated or more interesting,
看起来更复杂或更有趣，
let's say we have four clients,
假设我们有四个客户端，
which we're going to bring out this issue of consistency definitions more clearly,
我们将更清楚地提出一致性定义这一问题，
and it also does a read of x,
它也读取 x ，
well after you know the client 3 actually read x.
在客户端 3 读到了 x 之后。
So now we have some state,
所以现在我们有了一些状态，
what is desired outcomes,
什么是期望的结果，
what is incorrect outcomes,
什么是不正确的结果，
and that's really what defines consistency.
这就是一致性的真正定义。
So, let's take the first case C3,
那么，让我们来看第一种情况 C3 ，
you know what be a reasonable outcome for read C, read,
什么是一个合理的结果，
what is reasonable outcome for the read of C3 to return,
对于 C3 的读取来说，什么是合理的结果，
what values,
什么值，
you know what value would make you happy,
什么值会让你开心，
or make an application programmer happy.
或者让应用程序程序员开心。
2.
2.
2 be very reasonable?
2 很合理吗？
Any other reasonable values?
还有其他合理的值吗？
1.
1.
Yeah, 1 would be reasonable,
是的， 1 是合理的，
because the operation happened concurrently,
因为操作是同时进行的，
so maybe we don't really know which one,
所以也许我们不知道哪一个，
we don't really want to restrict what particular order they go,
我们并不想限制它们的具体顺序，
so we gone say like either one to fine,
所以我们说随便哪一个都可以，
because run concurrently.
因为是并行运行的。
What are some values that we would like not to see,
有哪些值观是我们不想看到的，
for the C3 read.
对于 C3 读取。
7.
7.
Yeah, 7, any other value, right,
是的， 7 ，任何其他的值，
because nobody wrote that,
因为没人写过这些，
so that would be undesirable.
所以这是不受欢迎的。
Okay, so good, so like we agree that,
好的，所以我们一致认为，
probably the reasonable outcome for C3 would be either 1 or 2.
c3 的合理结果可能是 1 或 2 。
Okay, how about C4?
好的，那么 C4 呢？
The same as c3.
与 C3 相同。
Really, exactly the same?
是吗，一样的吗？
So, let's say C3 return 1,
所以，假设 C3 返回 1 ，
what do we expect C4 to return?
我们期望 C4 返回什么？
Whatever C3 saw.
C3看到的值。
Yeah, because it run after C3, right,
是的，因为它是在 C3 之后运行的，
if 1 was returned, we expect 1 here too,
如果返回 1 ，我们希望这里是 1 ，
if 2 was returned, we expect 2 here.
如果返回 2 ，我们希望这里也是 2 。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Okay, so, you know there's like super brief you know sort of introduction
好的，所以，这是一个很简短的介绍，
of saying how can we define consistency,
说明我们如何定义一致性，
and typically we do this using sort of [traces],
通常我们使用 traces ，
and we argue about what correctness for particular [traces],
我们讨论特定[traces]的正确性，
and we will see more of that.
我们将看到更多这样的情况。
Of course, you know the server can enforce you know this kind of concurrency
当然，服务器可以强制这种并发性，
by for example using locks,
例如使用锁，
if you have done,
如果你已经这样做了，
if you do mapreduce,
如果你做了 mapreduce ，
you know of any concurrent Go programming you're write,
任何你写的并发 Go 程序，
that sort of the standard technique to enforce consistency in terms of,
那是强制一致性的标准技术，
in the presence of concurrency is to use locks.
在并发存在的情况下使用锁。
In distributed system,
在分布式系统中，
you know the ideal consistency you know sort of [] two hazards,
理想的一致性有两种风险，
and the second hazard is basically failure,
第二种风险是故障，
so just replication in general,
所以一般是复制，
for if we have two servers [],
如果我们有两台服务器，
so here's S1, here's S2,
所以这是 S1 ，这是 S2 ，
and you know both have a disk,
两个都有磁盘，
and we have our same clients as before, C1 and C2,
我们有和之前一样的客户端， C1 和 C2 ，
and they write you know to x,
它们向 x 写入，
and you know let's say you know just to illustrate what kind of complication,
只是为了说明什么样的复杂性，
what kind of, illustrate that we have to do something,
说明我们必须做些什么，
let's start with the most you know dumb replication plan.
让我们从最笨的复制方案开始。
So what very bad replication plan,
一个非常糟糕的复制方案，
so this particular bad replication kind of plan,
所以这个特别糟糕的复制方案，
what we're gonna do is,
我们要做的是，
like, we're gonna allow a client,
比如，我们将允许客户端，
when a client actually wants to update or write,
当客户端想要更新或写入时，
we're gonna tell it to
我们要告诉它，
basically you know the protocol that we're going to follow is,
我们跟据的协议是，
the client write to both servers,
将客户端写入到两台服务器，
in you know whatever,
无论什么，
don't really coordinate, just write to both.
不用协调，只需写入到两者。
And so exactly we have client 1, client 2 running,
我们有客户端 1 ，客户端 2 在运行，
you know then you know may be client 2 does the same thing,
然后，客户端 2 可能会做同样的事情，
and, and then we're going to ask ourselves the same question,
然后，我们会问自己同样的问题，
what does you know C3 see what actually read,
C3 实际读到的是什么，
and let's assume that for reading,
让我们假设读取，
you know say like we're either way,
无论使用哪种方式，
we're gonna read from any replica,
我们会从任何复制中读取，
as I said, is a very bad replication plan,
像我说的，这是一个非常糟糕的复制方案，
basically there's no restrictions.
没有任何限制。
So what are the possible outcomes?
那么，可能的结果是什么？
So this guy writes 1, this guy writes 2,
这个写入 1 ，这个写入 2 ，
and you know we C3,
我们是 C3 ，
what are the possible outcomes for C3?
C3 的可能结果是什么？
1 and 2, again.
还是 1 和 2 。
Yeah, 1 and 2, that really bad happens.
是的， 1 和 2 ，这真的很糟糕。
How about C4,
C4 怎么样，
we do a read of x, well after C3 x,
我们读取 x ，在 C3 读取 x 之后，
like this in the previous board.
像在上一个白板上一样。
Also 1 and 2.
也是 1 和 2 。
Yeah, 1 and 2 again,
是的，也是 1 和 2 ，
what happens C3 reads 1, but C4 may return?
如果 C3 读取 1 ，但 C4 可能返回什么？
1 or 2.
1 或 2 。
1 or 2, it's that what we want or not?
1 或 2 ，这是我们想要的吗？
No.
不是。
No, I mean you know,
不，我是说，
again, it would be difficult for an application writer
对于应用程序编写者来说，
to actually read about this,
很难读取这个，
you know particularly if the C3 and C4 were the same thing,
特别是 C3 和 C4 是一回事，
you first read to [] 1, no modification makes,
你首先读取 1 ，没有任何修改，
the next second returns another value,
然后下一秒返回另一个值，
how is that possible,
这怎么可能，
and it make the application programmers difficult to write.
这使得程序员很难编写程序。
And so you know the reason of course
所以原因当然是，
that this inconsistency shows up here,
这里显示的不一致性，
because we basically have no protocol
因为我们没有协议，
to coordinate you know the clients the readers and the writers,
来协调客户端，读取者和写入者，
so we need some form of distributed system,
所以我们需要某种形式的分布式系统，
typically we need some form of protocol to fix these,
我们需要某种形式的协议来解决这些问题，
and get the desire
并获得，
to enforce that we get the desired consistency.
确保我们获得所需的一致性。
So we can see in rest of the semester,
所以我们可以在这学期剩下的时间里看到，
a whole bunch of potential protocols,
很多可能的协议，
they have different trade-offs in terms of fault tolerance and consistency.
它们在容错和一致性方面有不同的权衡。
Okay?
好的?
And in fact you should get into get our head in that kind of thinking,
你应该有这样的想法，
the we're gonna use a whole bunch of different case studys,
我们要用很多不同的案例研究，
and the case study today is GFS.
今天的案例研究是 GFS 。
And this is an interesting case study,
这是一个有趣的案例研究，
you know why we would assign it,
为什么我们布置它，
and one reason is an interesting case study,
其中一个原因是有趣的案例研究，
because it brings out all these core issue.
因为它提出了所有这些核心问题。
GFS design designed to get high performance,
GFS 设计旨在获得高性能，
yeah, that means it actually uses replication and fault tolerance,
这意味着它使用了复制和容错，
and you know it struggles with consistency,
而且它很难保持一致性，
so it's like a few for sort of themes,
所以这就是一些主题，
that we're going to be consistently seeing it throughout the semester,
我们将在整个学期中持续看到它，
will show up in this one paper.
都会出现在这篇论文中。
The other side of this why is interesting case study,
为什么是有趣的案例研究的另一个原因，
because it is a successful system,
因为它是一个成功的系统，
Google does actually use GFS,
Google 确实使用了 GFS ，
at at this, at this point, in my understanding,
现在，据我所知，
there's a successor file system called Colossus,
有一个后继文件系统，名为 Colossus ，
you know but it's inspired by GFS,
但它的灵感来自于 GFS ，
and but there are other sort of cluster-based file systems,
还有其他类型的基于集群的文件系统，
you know for like mapreduce type used HDFS,
比如 mapreduce 类型使用的 HDFS ，
you know also very much inspired by the design of GFS.
也是从 GFS 的设计获取的灵感。
And you know one thing that is actually interesting,
有一件事其实很有趣，
at the point that this paper was written,
在写这篇论文的时候，
in sort of late to 2000,
在差不多 2000 年的时候，
it was pretty distributed file system were well understood topics,
分布式文件系统是容易理解的主题，
so people knew about fault tolerance,
人们知道容错，
and they knew about replication,
他们知道复制，
people knew about consistency,
人们知道一致性，
all that kind of stuff were pretty well understood.
所有这些事情都很容易理解。
However, nobody actually built you know system
然而，没有人构建出系统，
you know at the scale of thousands of computers,
在上千台计算机的规模上，
and that sure brings out a number of challenges,
这肯定会带来一些挑战，
that previous system have to not address,
以前的系统不能解决的，
and in fact the design is not completely standard,
而且设计也不完全规范，
so the design that we're reading about,
所以，我们正在看的设计，
it's not was not sort of the standard design,
不是某种标准的设计，
that you would see in academic papers at that time,
你会在当时的学术论文中看到，
there were two aspects of making non-standard,
有两个方面是非标准的，
[] which will get more we'll spend more time on.
[]我们会把更多的时间花在上面。
One is you know there's actually a single master,
一个是这里只有一个 master ，
the master, it's not replicated,
master 不是复制的，
there's a single machine that sort of charged
只有一台机器负责
with like almost all the coordination in the system,
系统中几乎所有的协调，
and so that is unusual,
所以这是不寻常的，
you know why would you build file system fault tolerance system,
为什么构建文件系统容错系统，
which has a single point of failure,
却包含单点故障，
is not something that people in the academic literature were doing at that time,
而不是当时学术文献中的人正在做的事情，
and the second thing is that,
第二件事是，
it has, it has not consistent,
它有不一致，
you know it can have inconsistencies,
它可能有不一致之处，
and again mostly in literature in at that particular time,
同样地，在那个时期的文献上，
you know people were really sweating actually to build
人们非常努力地构建
the distributed systems that actually have strong consistency,
具有强一致性的分布式系统，
and you know don't have the anomalies,
而且没有异常情况，
that we saw on the previous board.
我们在上一个白板上看到的那样。
Alright, and so so even though like a lot of the core techniques you know were well known,
好的，就像你所熟知的许多核心技术一样，
you know the way you were putting together essentially quite different.
你把它们放在一起的的方式是完全不同的。
And so, that makes it interesting,
因此，这让它变得有趣，
and particularly the scale which you know this system actually operates is impressive.
特别是这个系统实际运行的规模是令人印象深刻的。
And pretty common even for today,
即使在今天也很常见，
you know this issue,
这个问题，
struggle between fault tolerance, replication performance and consistency
在容错，复制性能和一致性之间的斗争，
is standard problem,
是一个标准问题，
recurring problems for almost any distributed storage system,
几乎是任何分布式存储系统重复出现问题，
so that people built today.
今天的人们构建的。
It changes over time,
它随着时间的推移而改变，
like S3 for a while,
比如 S3 有一段时间，
you know they really have that strong consistency,
它们真的有强一致性，
lately it has gotten much stronger consistency.
随后，它的一致性变得更强了。
Okay, so what, since the paper is really driven,
好的，因为论文驱动，
and the design is driven by fault tolerance by performance,
设计是由性能驱动的，
I wanted to go back to the mapreduce paper for second,
我想暂时回到 mapreduce 论文上，
and this is a graph of the mapreduce paper,
这是一张 mapreduce 的图，
and one way to think about GFS is,
考虑 GFS 的一种方式是，
that it's the file system for mapreduce,
它是 mapreduce 的文件系统，
and so the goal is
所以，我们的目标是，
to actually run many mapreduce jobs and get high performance.
运行多个 mapreduce 作业并获得高性能。
And we know that basically from,
我们知道这是从，
we could tell from the mapreduce paper already
我们已经可以从 mapreduce 的论文中看出，
that GFS is impressive in that manner in terms of performance.
GFS 在性能方面令人印象深刻。
So if you look at the you know this side of this graph,
所以如果你看这张图的这一边，
this is straight out of the mapreduce paper,
这是从 mapreduce 论文中拿出来的，
this is the normal execution of one of the mapreduce jobs,
这是一个 mapreduce 作业的正常执行，
and you know it has three parts to it,
它有三个部分，
one is the first part input,
一个是第一部分的输入，
like reading the input files,
比如，读取输入文件，
the inputs to the map from the file system,
从文件系统到 map 的输入，
and in case you know they didn't say much about it,
他们没怎么说这件事，
but those are written read from GFS,
但这些都是从 GFS 读写的，
there's the internal shuffle that we really care about,
这是我们关心的内部的 shuffle ，
and then at the end,
然后在最后，
you know the reduce jobs write back the results into GFS.
reduce 作业将结果写回 GFS 。
And, and so, do performance, you know part of the performance,
所以，部分性能，
there's mapreduce task is able to determined by
mapreduce 任务决定于,
you know the read at which,
从哪里读取，
the mappers can actually read you know data from GFS file system,
mapper 可以从 GFS 文件系统中读取数据，
so whatever we're running many, many mappers at the same time,
无论我们同时运行多少 mapper ，
in fact some mappers from different jobs maybe reading the same files.
一些来自不同作业的 mapper 可能会读取相同的文件。
So we look at the input,
所以我们来看一下输入，
like this, this there's top you know graph,
比如这里的最上面的图，
shows the input in terms of megabytes per second,
以兆字节/秒为单位的显示输入，
at the read at which you know the mapper
mapper 的读取，
actually jointly collectively for one particular job,
[为一项工作共同工作]，
you can read from the file system.
可以从文件系统中读取。
As you can see,
正如你所看到的，
you know it goes over, well over a thousand or 10 000 megabytes per second.
它通过超过每秒 10000 兆字节。
And you know the first question to ask you is,
你要问的第一个问题是，
maybe exactly an impressive number,
当然是一个令人印象深刻的数字，
should we be impressed with that number are,
我们对这个数字印象深刻，
thinking well, you know give me one disk and I do too.
考虑给我一个磁盘，我也可以做。
Anybody?
有人吗？
I think, because it's older, maybe yes.
我想是的，因为它很老了，也许是的。
Okay, SSD, how much what rates can you write read?
好的，固态硬盘，读写速率是多少？
Okay, let me tell you this,
好吧，让我告诉你，
roughly the throughput of a single disk at the time this, this paper
在论文发表的当时，一个磁盘的吞吐量大概是
was around like thirty megabytes per second,
30 兆字节每秒，
but somewhere in the tens of megabytes a second,
有时在每秒几十兆字节，
so here we're looking at
所以这里我们看到，
you know well over 10000 megabytes per second, correct,
超过 10000 兆字节每秒，
and so that is an impressive number.
这是一个令人印象深刻的数字。
And you know you have to work
你必须做些工作，
as you know the seeing,
正如你所看到的，
the GFS design that allows that kind of throughput.
GFS 设计允许这种吞吐量。
Of course, this technology indications GFS,
当然，这项技术表明 GFS ，
of course this technology was faster,
当然，这项技术更快，
it would be you know what the real goal here correctly,
这里真正的目标是什么，
it's like we have a thousand machines,
我们有一千台机器，
maybe each one has a disk,
也许每个机器都有一个磁盘，
each one read thirty megabytes per second,
每一个都读取每秒 30 兆字节，
which is 1000 times thirty megabytes per second to get out of it.
这是 1000 乘以 30 兆字节每秒才能[摆脱]它。
Okay?
好的?
So that't what you know drives a lot of this design is,
所以这个设计的驱动是，
to immediately allow the mappers to read in parallel from the file system,
允许 mapper 从文件系统并行读取，
joint file system.
[联合]的文件系统。
Okay?
好的?
Let me say a little bit more about this,
关于这个，让我再说一点，
about what are the key properties that GFS has,
GFS 的关键属性是什么，
you know one big large data sets,
一个大的数据集，
remember that, I mean that,
我的意思是，
and so in the think the data set you should think about is like mapreduce data sets,
你应该考虑的数据集就像 mapreduce 数据集，
you're going to have a complete crawl the world wide web,
你将爬取整个万维网，
is stored in this distributed file system.
存储在这个分布式文件系统中。
Has to be fast,
必须要快，
we talked about,
我们谈到了，
the way they get like high performance is to do automatic sharding,
他们获得高性能的方法是进行自动分片，
shard files across multiple disks,
分片文件到多个磁盘，
allow multiple clients to read from those disks in parallel.
允许多个客户端从这些磁盘并行读取。
Alright?
好的？
It goes global,
它是全局的，
what that mean it's shared,
这意味着它是共享的，
you know all apps see same file system,
所以应用看到相同的文件系统，
and that's convenient,
这很方便，
like if you have multiple mapreduce jobs,
例如，如果你有多个 mapreduce 作业，
you know that operate on the same set of files,
对同一组文件进行操作，
they can, first of all read all the same set of files,
首先，它们可以读取所有相同的文件集，
then they can produce new files,
然后它们可以制作新文件，
and another mapreduce you can use those files again,
另一个 mapreduce 再次使用这些文件，
and so it's very convenient to have a lot of sharing between applications,
所以，在应用程序之间进行大量共享非常方便，
so it's very convenient to have.
所以拥有它是非常方便的。
Of course, you know the GFS has to be fault tolerant,
当然， GFS 必须具有容错能力，
it's likely they're gonna be failures,
它们很可能会失败，
it's what we want like automatic,
我们想要自动的，
close to automatic fault tolerance as possible,
尽可能自动容错，
you'll see GFS doesn't provide completely automatic,
你会发现 GFS 并不是完全自动的，
but do a pretty good job with getting high with fault tolerance.
但在提高容错能力方面做得相当好。
Okay, any questions about the, this part so far,
好的，到目前为止，关于这一部分，有什么问题吗，
like a broad intro to this topic,
对这个主题的宽泛介绍，
few intro [] about GFS.
关于 GFS 的几个介绍。
Okay.
好的。
Let's then talk about the design.
然后让我们来讨论一下设计。
So here's the design,
这里的设计，
is seen in from the figure one I think in the paper,
是从论文中图一看到的，
and there's a couple things I wanted to point out,
有几件事我想指出，
talk a little bit more in detail about.
更详细地讨论一些细节。
So, first of all, you know, we have an application,
所以，首先，我们有一个应用程序，
and then you know the application again you know might be mapreduce job,
然后这个应用程序可能是 mapreduce 作业，
consists multiple reduce task, multiple map task,
包含多个 reduce 任务，多个 map 任务，
and they link with the GFS,
它们与 GFS 关联，
like and so, it's not a Linux file system,
它不是 Linux 文件系统，
you know this is not the file system,
这不是（普通的）文件系统，
you used to you know whatever edit files or compile,
你用来编辑文件或编译，
it is really intended,
它是一个专门用于，
you know as a special purpose file system for these large computations.
这些大型计算的文件系统。
And as I said before,
正如我之前所说，
our real goal correctly achieves an impressive number,
我们的真正目标是实现一个令人印象深刻的数字，
like we want the number of megabytes from a single disk times number of machines,
比如我们想要单个磁盘的兆字节数乘以机器数量，
and a single application should be able to exploit that.
单个应用程序应该能够利用这个。
So the way they arrange that is to have a master,
所以他们安排的方式是有一个 master ，
that is basically in charge of actually know where things are,
它负责东西在哪里，
and the clients just periodically talks to the master,
客户端只是周期性地与 master 交互，
to to retrieve information,
为了获得信息，
so for example it opens the file,
例如，它会打开文件，
and open call will result in a message to the master,
打开调用将导致向 master 发送一条消息，
and the master will respond back
master 将回复，
and say like all the particular filename,
表示所有指定的文件名，
the chunks that you need are here,
你需要的块在这里，
well, these are the chunks that you need,
好的，这些是你需要的块，
and there's a chunk handles identifier
并且有一个块句柄标识符，
for the particular chunks that constitute a file,
对应那个文件包含的块，
and here are the servers that sure that chunk,
这是块数据的服务器，
so you get back chunk handle as well as a bunch of chunk locations.
你可以得到块句柄以及很多块位置。
And one file might you know basically file consists,
一个文件可能包含，
if you think about a big file,
如果你考虑一个大文件，
it consists of many many chunks,
它由许多块组成，
chunk 0, chunk 1, chunk 2, etc, chunk 3 blah, blah, etc, etc,
块 0 、块 1 、块 2 、块 3 等等，
any chunk is pretty big, 64 megabytes,
任何块都是很大的， 64 兆字节，
naturally, the application wants we you know second second second 64 megabyte,
应用程序想要第二个 64 兆字节，
it goes to the GFS
它告诉 GFS ，
is like okay, I wanna read you the second chunk,
我想读取第二块，
you know this particular file,
这个特定的文件，
and the GFS answer, will answer back with the handle for chunk 1,
GFS 将使用块 1 的句柄进行应答，
as well as the servers that actually holds chunk 1, right.
以及保存块 1 的服务器。
So multiple applications might ask you know for chunks from the same file,
多个应用程序可能会要求从同一文件中获取块，
and they all get you know
它们都会得到，
one application might be reading chunk 0,
一个应用程序可能正在读取块 0 ，
another application might be read chunk 2,
另一应用程序可能读取块 2 ，
they'll get different lists back for each of these chunks.
它们将得到不同的列表，对应这些块。
So then the GFS client you know once it knows chunk locations,
一旦 GFS 客户端知道了块位置，
and basically straight talks to the chunk servers,
就会直接与块服务器交互，
and basically read you know the data at the speed of the network,
以网络的速度读取数据，
and you know maybe every disk you know sits behind this particular chunk server,
可能每个磁盘都位于特定的区块服务器后面，
directly to the application.
直接连接到应用程序。
And here you can see where we're going to get the big win, right,
这里你可以看到，我们获得了重大胜利，
because we're gonna be able to read,
因为我们能够读取，
you know for multiple,
对于多个，
you know multiple clients can be read from multiple disks at the same time,
多个客户端可以同时从多个磁盘读取，
and we're going to get tremendous amount of performance,
我们将获得巨大的性能，
so for example, like here's map task running,
比如，这是一个运行的 map 任务，
here's another map tasks running,
这是另一个正在运行的 map 任务，
that also as a client,
也是作为客户端，
you know they you know going to be talking to the set of servers,
它们会和一组服务器交互，
we have that whole you know the chunk of all the collection the data set,
有一个完整的所有数据集的块的集合，
and there's gonna read in parallel
它们会并行读取，
from all those different chunk servers,
从所有不同的块服务器，
and that was going to give us a high throughput number.
这会给我们一个很高的吞吐量数字。
Is that makes sense,
这能理解吗，
that's sort of the overall plan clear here.
这是总体方案。
Just to sort of completed,
为了解释完整，
like on chunk server is nothing really else,
块服务器不是别的，
and sort of a Linux box, Linux computer with you know disk to it,
只是有磁盘的 Linux 计算机，
in fact there's 64 megabyte chunk,
实际上，是 64 兆字节的块，
each store as a Linux file, in the Linux file system.
每个都作为一个 Linux 文件存储在 Linux 文件系统中。
Okay?
好的?
Okay, so I want to zoom in on the different pieces
好的，我想把不同的部分放大，
and I'll start with the master,
我先从 master 开始，
because masters are related to the control center here,
因为 master 跟这里的控制中心有关，
so talk a little bit about the state that actually the master maintains.
所以，讨论一下 master 维护的状态。
Okay, so first of all,
好的，首先，
you know it has the mapping from file name to an array of of chunk handles,
它有从文件名到块句柄数组的映射，
and as you saw in the paper,
正如你在论文上看到的，
one of the goals,
其中一个目标，
actually is to maintain all this memory of,
是维护所有这些内存，
most of the information actually directly available in memory,
大多数信息直接在内存中，
so that master response to a client very quickly,
所以 master 可以非常快速地响应客户端，
and the reason why reason to do that is because,
而这么做的原因是因为，
now there's one master, many clients,
现在只有一个 master ，很多客户端，
you want to execute every client operation as efficient as possible,
你希望尽可能高效地执行每个客户端操作，
so that you can scale the master to at least a reasonable number of clients,
这样就可以将 master 扩展到合理数量的客户端，
and then, for every chunk handle,
然后，对于每个块句柄，
the master contains some additional number,
master 包含一些额外的数字，
it make particular, it maintains a version number,
它维护一个版本号，
and a list of chunk servers,
和一个块服务器列表，
that holds a copy of that chunk.
里面有块的复制。
And as we'll see in a second,
正如我们稍后会看到的，
you know one of them is named,
其中一个名字叫做，
one of those servers are primary,
其中一台服务器是主服务器，
and the other ones are secondary,
而其他的则是次要的，
and the typical number that you know a chunk stored at 3 servers
典型数量是块存储在 3 台服务器上，
and we can maybe talk a little bit later about why 3.
我们可以过一会儿再谈为什么是 3 .
And then you know there is a lease associated with each primary,
然后每个主服务器有一个释放时间，
so there's a lease time maintained as well.
所以，也维持一个释放时间。
Then there's two sort of other big storage components,
然后还有两个大的存储组件，
and these are sort of the file system level things,
这些都是文件系统级别的东西，
and then in terms of implementation, there's a log,
然后在实施方面，有一个日志，
and there are checkpoints。
还有检查点.
Since the master of the crucial control center,
因为 master 是关键的控制中心，
whenever there's change to the name space,
每当名称空间发生更改时，
and potentially create a new file in the GFS,
可能在 GFS 中创建新文件，
or mapping the file to chunk blocks and changes,
或者将文件映射到块和改变，
all those operations are written to this log,
所有这些操作都会写入这个日志，
and log sits on stable storage.
而日志存放在稳定的存储里。
And the basic idea is that,
基本的想法是，
like we were before responding to the client,
在回应客户端之前，
the change actually has made the master writes to stable storage first,
改变使 master 首先写入稳定存储器，
and then responds to the client,
然后对客户端进行响应，
so this means that if the master fails or crashes,
所以，这意味着如果 master 出现故障或崩溃，
then later comes back up,
然后又回来了，
it can replay log to reconstruct you know the state of its internal state,
它可以通过重放日志来重建它的内部状态，
and by writing it first to a storage before responding to the client,
通过在响应客户端之前首先将其写入存储器，
the client will never observe strange results,
客户端永远不会观察到奇怪的结果，
you know you could do the other way around correct,
你可以用另一种方式，
that result in a problem,
但那会导致一个问题，
because you know the client will think that the file has been created,
因为客户端会认为文件已创建，
server crash backup and then the file doesn't exist,
服务器崩溃回复，然后文件就不存在了，
so, these are another consistency point.
所以，这是另一个一致性关键点。
You know replaying always back all the operations
重放总是所有操作，
from the beginning of time to log is of course undesirable,
从开始时间到日志当然是不想要的，
it means that if the master crashes,
这意味着如果 master 崩溃，
and we have only one of them will be down for a long time,
我们只有一个，会停机很长一段时间，
so in addition to that,
所以除此之外，
you know it actually keeps checkpoints in stable storage,
它也会将检查点保存在稳定存储中，
so periodically, the master makes a checkpoint of its own state
所以， master 会定期创建自己状态的检查点，
and the mapping [] array chunk handles,
和映射[]块句柄，
and stores that on on the stable storage,
并将其存储在稳定的存储上，
and so then they only have to replay the last part,
然后它们只需要重放最后一段，
basically all the operations in the log after the last checkpoint,
日志中最后一个检查点之后的所有操作，
so the recovery is actually quickly.
所以，恢复是很快的。
So, there's another couple interesting questions,
所以，还有另外几个有趣的问题，
that we can ask ourselves,
我们可以问自己，
like what state does need to end up in a stable storage,
比如什么状态需要放在一个稳定的存储里，
you know for the master actually function correctly.
对于 master 的功能来说。
So the first question to ask is,
所以第一个要问的问题是，
how about this array of chunk handles the mapping from filename to chunk handles,
这个从文件名到块句柄的映射需要吗，
does that need to be stable stored,
它需要稳定储存吗，
or can it be only in memory.
或者它可以只存在于内存中。
If the master crashes,
如果 master 崩溃，
I think you can like get that information from the servers, chunk servers,
我想你可以从块服务器获得信息，
so maybe only, may memory.
所以也许只是在内存中。
Yeah, well, that's answer the question,
是的，这是问题的答案，
what other people think.
其他人是怎么想的。
So it can be reconstructed from the log,
所以它可以从日志中重建出来，
so, when the server crashes,
所以当服务器崩溃时，
only the log needs to be in the hard storage,
只有日志需要存储在硬盘中，
and then it can reload it from the log to main memory.
然后它可以从日志重新加载到主存中。
Yeah, so definitely has to be in log,
是的，它肯定在日志中，
so we agree that,
所以我们同意，
this array of chunk handles basically has to be stored in stable storage,
这个块句柄列表必须存储在稳定的存储中，
because otherwise we lose,
否则，我们会丢失，
like we create a file,
比如我们创建一个文件，
and we didn't write the storage,
我们没有写入存储，
we just lose the file right,
我们就把文件丢了，
so this mapping from filename to chunk handles need to be in a stable storage,
所以，从文件名到块句柄的这种映射需要在稳定的存储中，
how about this chunk handle to chunk handle to list of chunk servers,
那么从块句柄到块服务器列表需要吗，
is that actually you need to be [].
它需要[]吗？
I think in the paper,
我想在论文中，
they say that when the master reboots,
他们说当 master 重新启动时，
it asks the servers to tell tell the master,
它要求服务器告诉 master ，
what the chunks that they have are.
它们拥有的块是什么。
Yeah, so this is not actually,
是的，所以这不是，
this is basically just volatile state, not not stable storage.
这只是易失性状态，而不是稳定的存储。
So same presumably to the primaries and the secondaries, and to the lease time.
同样的，对于主要的和次要的，以及释放时间。
How about the version number?
那么版本号呢？
Does the master need to remember on stable storage version number or not?
master 是否需要将版本号记到稳定存储中？
Yes, because it needs to know
是的，因为它需要知道，
if the chunks in the other servers are stale or not.
其他服务器中的块是否是旧的。
Yeah, exactly exactly right, right,
是的，完全正确，
so the master must remember version number,
所以 master 必须记住版本号，
because if it doesn't,
因为如果它不这么做，
and the whole system went down,
整个系统崩溃了，
and the chunk servers came back up,
然后块服务器又恢复了，
and maybe the chunk server actually with the most recent data does not come up,
可能块服务器包含最新的还没有出现的数据，
with an older guy comes up with version number 14,
是一个旧的版本号 14 ，
then the master has to be able to tell
然后， master 必须能够区分，
that you know that chunk server version of 14 was not the most recent chunk server,
版本是 14 的块服务器不是最新的块服务器，
and so it needs to maintain that version number on disk,
所以，它需要在磁盘上维护版本号，
so that actually can tell,
可以用来区分，
which chunk servers actually have the most updated information on which ones don't.
哪个块服务器拥有最新信息，哪个没有。
Okay?
好的?
I have a question here,
我有一个问题，
if, well, I mean if if the master failed
如果 master 失败了，
and then it has to come up,
然后它再次出现，
it's anyway going to connect to all of the chunk servers,
无论如何，它都会连接到所有块服务器，
and it will find out what the largest version is.
它会找到最大的版本是什么。
Yeah, has ability to find out what the last,
是的，有能力找出最新的，
first of all, it will try to talk to all chunk servers,
首先，它尝试与所有块服务器进行交互，
some chunk servers might be down.
一些块服务器可能已经关闭。
Okay.
好的。
And that's that maybe just the chunk server,
有可能就是那台块服务器，
that actually has the most recent version right.
正好有最新版本。
Yeah, okay.
是的，好的。
So you can't take the max of the life chunk servers,
所以，你不能使用最大的寿命的块服务器，
that be incorrect.
这是不正确的。
Any other questions about this?
对于这个，还有其他问题吗？
Okay, let's look at the two sort of basic operations,
好的，让我们来看看两种基本运算，
to really get down to consistency,
真正做到一致性，
and of course you know it's going to be reading and writing,
当然，这是读取和写入，
so reading a file,
所以读取一个文件，
and then we'll talk about writing a file.
然后我们讨论如何写入文件。
So reading files in some sense straightforward,
从某种意义上说，读取文件很简单，
we talked about basically a client send message
我们谈到的客户端发送消息，
you know to with the filename plus offset to the master,
使用文件名加上偏移量给 master ，
and basically ask please give me you know chunk servers,
询问请给我块服务器，
and chunk handle that hold that hold the data at that offset,
以及在偏移量处保存数据的块句柄，
and so end finds the chunk handle,
所以找到块句柄，
so like read byte whatever 0,
比如读取字节 0 ，
you know it's pretty clear that has to be the first entry in the list,
很明显，这是列表上的第一个条目，
you know from filename to chunk handle.
从文件名到块句柄。
So [], the master chunk handle basically replies you know with the master,
所以， master 块句柄与 master 一起回复，
replies to the client with the chunk handle,
用块句柄回复客户端，
and list of chunk servers for that handle and version number.
以及那个句柄的块服务器列表和版本号。
So basically the client gets back a message
所以客户端会收到一条消息，
saying you know that's chunk you know 221,
表示这是块 221 ，
you know and here are the three machines,
并且这是三台机器，
IP address, the three machines that actually have it,
这三台机器所有的 IP 地址，
and the version number is like version of 10.
并且版本号比如是 10 。
Then the client caches this list,
然后，客户端缓存这个列表，
and then it basically sends a message to the closest,
然后它向最近的服务器发送一条消息，
reads from closest server.
从最近的服务器读取。
And so why this the client actually read cache this information,
那么为什么客户端缓存这些信息，
yes, we'll see later, correct,
我们稍后再看，
that caused some troubles.
那造成了一些麻烦。
So it doesn't have to contact the master for some time,
所以它在一段时间内不需要联系 master ，
if it wants to read again or write to that chunk.
如果它想要再次读取或写入块。
Yeah, why is that important?
是的，这个为什么重要？
To reduce the, I guess the traffic,
为了减少流量，
and in general it takes less time,
一般来说，会花费更少的时间，
if you have less communication with the master.
如果你与 master 的通信更少。
Yeah, and you know the, you do the same with that's correct,
是的，这是正确的，
this design is that the master actually a single machine,
这种设计 master 是一台机器，
and as a single machine,
作为一台机器，
you can just have a limited amount of memory and limit network interface,
你只拥有有限的内存和有限的网络接口，
and so you have too many clients talking to,
你有太多的客户端交互，
it wouldn't be able to serve, right,
它就不能服务了，
so client caching is important to reduce the load on this single machine.
所以，客户端缓存对于减少这台机器上的负载很重要。
Okay, why read from the closest server?
好的，为什么要从最近的服务器上读取？
Minimize network traffic.
最大限度地减少网络流量。
Yeah, minimize network traffic,
是的，最大限度地减少网络流量，
you know, so the whole goal correct is,
所以整个目标是，
to pump as much data to client as possible,
为了将尽可能多的数据传输到客户端，
the highest throughput.
最高的吞吐量。
And you know we have, there's two problems,
这里面有两个问题，
we had to cross with data center network,
我们必须通过数据中心网络，
one you know where there's probably some topology,
一个可能有一些拓扑，
and maybe [swamps] like the top links of topology,
也许[]像顶层链接拓扑，
and may actually increase latency to actually get to the other side.
可能会增加到达另一边的延迟。
Alright, it's important to be able to be to the closest side,
好的，能够访问最近的一个是重要的，
again to basically maximize you know the throughput
同样，为了最大限度地提高吞吐量，
you know that joint set of clients,
它联合一组客户端，
you can sort of experience,
你可以得到，
when they're reading in parallel from many many chunk servers.
当它们从许多块服务器并行读取时。
Okay?
好的?
So the chunk server S you know [] check the version number,
所以块服务器 S 检查版本号，
and if the version number is okay,
如果版本号是正确的，
you know then send data.
然后发送数据。
Okay?
好的?
Why is check the version number there?
为什么在那里检查版本号？
To check if it's too stale.
检查它是不是太旧了。
Yeah, we do our best to avoid reading stale data,
是的，我们尽最大努力避免读取过时的数据，
and you know as we'll seen in a second,
我们马上就会看到，
we do you don't do a perfect job at [],
我们没有在[]方面做得完美，
but try hard to minimize you know occurrences with the clients reading stale data.
但是尽量减少客户端读取过时数据的情况。
Okay?
好的?
Those reading reasonable straightforward.
这些读取直截了当。
So let's look at the writing.
那么，让我们来看看写入。
So this is a picture from the paper,
这是论文上的一张图片，
and so let's say client was the,
所以我们假设客户端是，
let's focus append.
让我们来关注追加。
And so they argued that the very common operation for them
他们认为，对他们来说，这是非常常见的操作，
needs to append a record to a file,
需要将记录追加到文件中，
and can we see why,
我们能知道为什么，
given what you guys you know from mapreduce,
基于你们从 mapreduce 中了解到的情况，
you know Google does make sense,
你知道 Google 是有道理的，
why append is so important.
为什么追加如此重要。
Because largely in doing mapreduce,
因为在做 mapreduce 时，很大程度上，
you need to,
你需要，
as the map function spits out information,
当 map 函数发出信息时，
it's largely just adding on information
它在很大程度上只是增加信息，
rather than changing previously spit out information.
而不是修改之前已经发出的信息。
Yeah, you know maybe the map is not the best example,
是的，也许 map 不是最好的例子，
because write to the local files not to GFS,
因为它写入本地文件而不是 GFS ，
but the reducer does,
但是 reducer 是这样做的，
the same argument also reducer.
同样的论点也适用于 reducer 。
Yeah, so they're going to work there
是的，所以他们在那里工作，
at writings basically consume a lot of information,
写入消耗了大量的信息，
and you know append record soon to file,
很快地把记录附加到文件中，
with the resulting computation with result of the computation.
与计算结果一起。
Okay?
好的?
Good, so you know step 1 we have clients,
好的，所以第一步我们有客户端，
it will talk to the master to figure out where to write,
它与 master 交互，以确定在哪里写入，
and so the master looks in it's table,
master 查看表，
where the filename to chunk handles,
文件名到块句柄的表，
and finds you know the chunk handles,
找到块句柄，
and then you know looks at this table of chunk handles to servers,
然后查看块句柄到服务器的表，
to find the list of servers that has,
找到对应的服务器列表，
that have a particular thing,
包含指定的东西，
that have that particular chunk.
包含指定的块。
Okay, so what happens next,
好的，接下来会发生什么，
so there's two cases,
所以有两种情况，
when there's already primary,
当已经有 primary 时，
in the second case, the first case,
第二种情况，第一种情况，
with two cases having a primary or not primary.
两种情况是有 primary 或没有 primary 。
Let's say this is the very first time,
假设这是很早的第一次，
that this particular client contacts the master for this particular chunk,
这个客户端为了这个块访问 master ，
nobody else has done it so far,
还没有其他人这样做过，
so there's no primary,
所以还没有 primary ，
in that case, you know we need to do,
在这种情况下，我们需要做的是，
master needs to pick a primary, right,
master 需要选出一个 primary ，
how did it do that.
它是怎么做的。
I think the master just picks any of the available chunk servers, right.
我认为 master 可以选择任何可用的块服务器。
Yep, picks one,
是的，选出一个，
so picks one of those primary and other ones are the secondary,
所以选出一个是 primary 和其他的都是 secondary ，
what other steps are involved in this sort of.
在这种情况下，还涉及到哪些步骤。
Yeah, and then subsequently the master grants a lease to that primary,
是的，然后 master 给那个 primary 一个租约，
and that lease has a certain like date of expiry.
那个租约有明确的过期时间。
Yeah, what else do you have,
是的，还有什么，
one or more other piece of crucial information.
一条或多条其他关键信息。
Even.
Even。
Increment the version number?
增加版本号？
Yeah, yeah, step one is increment version number,
是的，第一步是增加版本号，
because you're gonna make a new primary,
因为你要有一个新的 primary ，
and when every time you make a new primary,
当你每次有新的 primary 时，
or whatever you make a new primary,
或者无论你有新的 primary ，
you go to sort of want to think about is a new epoch,
你需要考虑的是进入了一个新时期，
in the file system or this particular file,
在文件系统中或这个文件中，
and so you increase the version number,
所以增加版本号，
because you have a new data,
因为你有一个新的数据，
so basically the master increases the version number,
所以， master 会增加版本号，
yeah, it's sends to the primary a new version number and the secondaries,
它会给 primary 和 secondary 发送一个新的版本号，
and saying like hey guys we're gonna start a new,
然后说，我们要开始一个新的，
we will start a new mutation,
我们要开始一个新的改变，
you got for forming a replica group,
你需要形成一个复制组，
and your replica group with this particular version number whatever
你的复制组使用这个指定的版本号，
version number 12, right.
比如版本号 12 。
And the primary and the secondary store version number,
然后 primary 和 secondary 保存版本号，
what do you is store the version number,
你需要怎么保存版本号，
do they store on disk or on their disk or memory, or.
它们是存储在磁盘上还是内存上，或者。
I don't know.
我不知道。
Anyone, what do you think?
有人知道吗，你怎么想的？
Okay, let's first do memory,
好的，让我们放到内存里，
let's say storage in memory,
假设存储在内存中，
would that be a good design?
这是一个好的设计吗？
No.
不是。
Sorry.
抱歉。
You can go.
你可以继续。
I guess it wouldn't,
我想不是，
because if the chunk server goes down,
因为如果块服务器出现故障，
and then it comes back up,
然后它又回来了，
it, it should know what version it has.
它应该知道自己有什么版本。
Yeah, because otherwise you couldn't convince the primary
是的，因为否则你不能说服 primary ，
that has the most recent one,
你有最近一次的，
was the primary, sorry the master could big,
primary ，抱歉， master 可能会很大，
you know the chunk server with most recent data,
块服务器有最新的数据，
so it has to be on this,
所以它必须是这样，
so basically the version number lives on disk,
所以，版本号存储在磁盘上，
both at the chunk servers and at the master, right.
包括块服务器和 master 。
So when the chunk, the master gets back,
所以当 master 回来后，
you know the acknowledgement from the primary and secondary,
来自 primary 和 secondary 的确认，
that they written the version number to disk,
它们已经将版本号写入磁盘，
and in the primary actually has received the lease,
primary 收到了租约，
then you know the master also writes its version number to disk,
然后 master 也将它的版本号写入磁盘，
and then responds to the client.
然后对客户端作出响应。
Okay?
好的?
So to back to the client,
所以，要返回到客户端，
responds with a list of servers,
使用服务器列表作为响应，
you know primary plus secondary plus version number.
primary 加上 secondary 加上版本号。
Okay?
好的?
Then you know the next step,
然后下一步，
and again here we see the whole goal is
同样，我们在这里看到，整个目标是，
to [type] a lot of data from the network,
从网络中[输入]大量数据，
is the client actually just sends the data,
客户端只是发送数据，
that wants write to the to the primary and the secondary,
想要写入到 primary 和 secondary 的，
the way it actually does is sort of an interesting way,
它的工作方式是一种有趣的方式，
and basically contact the closest secondary it knows of,
联系它知道的最近的 secondary ，
you know out of this list,
在这个列表上，
and sends the data there,
并将数据发送到那里，
and that secondary you know move the data over to the next person in the list,
那个 secondary 将数据转移给列表中的第二个人，
and then to the next server list,
然后转给下一个服务器列表，
and so this way
通过这种方式，
you know the data sort of pumped from the clients
数据从客户端
you know to the pipeline to all the replicas,
发送到管道，到所有副本，
and you know when the secondary receives,
当 secondary 收到后，
the first secondary receives some of the data,
第一个 secondary 接收到一些数据，
immediately starts actually pushing the data further down the pipeline.
立即开始将数据推向管道。
Okay?
好的?
The reason this design is,
这种设计的原因是，
this way sort of basically this network interface,
这种方式的网络接口，
the client that has go to the outside world,
客户端走向[外面的世界]，
uses a full network interface to push the data down the pipeline,
使用全网络接口向管道推送数据，
so that gives us high throughput.
所以，这为我们提供了高吞吐量。
Okay?
好的?
Okay, so then you know if this all successful,
好的，如果这些都成功了，
and the data has been pushed you know to all the servers,
数据已经被推送到所有服务器，
those servers don't store that information in this yet,
这些服务器还不会存储信息，
and it just sits there sort of on the side,
它只是坐在一边，
you know to be used in the next step.
要在下一步中使用。
So the next step is,
所以下一步是，
basically for the client to send a message,
让客户端发送消息，
like an append message you know to the primary,
比如一个追加消息到 primary ，
and at that point,
在这一刻，
you know the primary will check you know the version number, right,
primary 会检查版本号，
whether it actually version number corresponds to the version number,
它的版本号是否匹配，
if it doesn't correspond to, if it doesn't match,
如果它不匹配，
then they probably won't allow it,
那么它们不会允许这样做，
the primary checks this lease, is the lease valid,
primary 检查这个租约是否有效，
because if lease is not valid anymore,
因为如果租约不再有效，
it cannot accept any mutation operations,
它不能接受任何改变操作，
because it if lease is not valid,
因为如果租约无效，
there might be another primary outside in the world,
外面的世界可能会有另一个 primary ，
so it checks the lease,
所以它会检查租约，
and then, if you know basically the version numbers match, the lease is still valid,
然后，如果版本号匹配，租约有效，
basically picks an offset to write there.
然后会选择一个偏移量来写入。
And then the next step is,
然后下一步是，
we basically write you know the data that just came in,
我们写下刚刚进来的数据，
you know this record to a stable storage,
这个记录到一个稳定存储，
so the primary actually at this point write it to stable storage,
所以，在这一点上， primary 将其写入稳定存储，
the data,
这个数据，
and then sends messages to the secondary,
然后将消息发送到 secondary ，
saying please write the data too.
表示请将数据写入。
And since the primary picks the offsets,
因为 primary 选择的偏移量，
you know the, it tells the secondaries,
它告诉 secondary ，
where to write you know that particular record into the file,
将记录写入文件的哪个位置，
so maybe you like whatever it takes offset 125,
比如你选择的偏移量是 125 ，
and it will tell the secondaries,
它会告诉 secondary ，
[] all to write you know the data that came in earlier at offset 125.
将早些时候进来的数据写入到偏移量 125 处。
Then, if everything workout,
然后，如果一切顺利，
you know everybody, all the secondary and the primary
所有 secondary 和 primary
successfully write their data back you know to disk,
都成功地将数据写入磁盘，
then it actually responds back to the client,
然后它会对客户端做出响应，
saying like okay success you append actually happens.
表示，好的，你追加已经成功了。
There's a way that the write actually might be not successful
存在一种方式，写入可能不成功，
or it might not be successful,
或可能不成功，
and namely for example, the primary has written into its own disk,
比如， primary 已写入自己的磁盘，
but it fails to write it,
但它没能写入，
you know it fails to connect to one of the secondaries,
它没能写入其中一个 secondary ，
maybe secondary actually crashed,
或许 secondary 崩溃了，
or maybe the secondary just has a network connection that doesn't work,
或者可能 secondary 的网络不工作了，
and in that case, the primary actually returns an error to the client,
在这种情况下， primary 会向客户端返回错误，
so error if one secondary didn't respond,
所以，如果一个 secondary 没有响应，就是错误的，
and in that case, the client library what it will do is usually try or retry,
在这种情况下，客户端库将执行的操作通常是重试，
it will reissue the same append and will try again,
它将重新发布相同的追加，并再次尝试，
in the hope that the second time around,
希望在第二次的时候，
you know that data actually, that [] get through,
这些数据能被通过，
and so this is what they call like you do at-least-once.
这就是他们所说的最少一次。
If you retry, will the primary pick the same offset?
如果重试， primary 会选取相同的偏移量吗？
I don't think so.
我不这样认为。
No, it needs a new offset
不，它需要一个新的偏移量，
and you know writes the, write new particular offset,
写入新的指定偏移量，
so that means if you look at the disks
这意味着如果你查看磁盘，
a file on the three replicas,
一个文件在三个副本上，
you know the primary S1 S2,
primary S1 和 S2 ，
it might be the case,
可能是这种情况，
something you wrote like you know S1 125 the data,
你写入 S1 125 数据，
we succeeded maybe S2 12,
我们成功可能 S2 12 ，
but S2 actually doesn't happen, there's no data, right,
但 S2 实际上并没有发生，没有数据，
and then we try again,
然后我们再试一次，
we might rather read the same data x,
我们可能读取相同的数据 x ，
and maybe we'll succeed in all three.
也许在三个副本上都成功了。
So you see here,
所以你可以在这里看到，
that basically replicates records can be duplicated.
副本的记录是可以重复的。
Is this something that can happen in a standard file system,
这在标准文件系统中可以发生吗，
like your Linux file system on your laptop or your computer.
比如在你的笔记本或计算机上的 Linux 文件系统。
No.
不会。
No, would you be surprised if your computer did this?
不，如果你的计算机做到这个，你会感到惊讶吗？
I mean, yeah,
我想是的，
this is not how standard file writes work.
这不是标准文件写入的工作方式。
Yeah, it would be inconvenient to have this property,
是的，有这个特性会不方便，
or it doesn't matter?
还是没什么关系？
Inconvenient.
不方便。
Yeah, gonna be a pretty bizarre,
是的，这会是非常奇怪的，
you know presumably like you know you compiler you produce outputs in your file,
编译器产生结果到文件中，
and then maybe you know certain blocks written twice,
然后，某些数据块写入了两次，
and then you can't run the program anymore,
然后你不能再运行程序了，
like you know the whole thing is just garbage at that point.
所有东西都变成了垃圾。
So it would just be weird,
所以这会很奇怪，
like you write an email message
就像你写了一封电子邮件，
and this is the body of the email message shows up twice.
而电子邮件的正文出现了两次。
So this is not your typical file system we do
所以，这不是典型的文件系统，
and so there's like a slightly bizarre
所以是有点奇怪的，
and you know what is the justification,
你知道理由是什么，
why, why, why do you think this is a good idea.
为什么你认为这是个好主意。
I'm not sure what is a good idea,
我不确定什么是好主意，
but I'm confused how that works for mapreduce specifically,
但我搞不懂这对 mapreduce 是如何起作用的，
so if you run word count and you do that,
如果你运行 word count ，并且这么做，
and like some files and you'll count,
一些文件，你会计数，
and they're like word a, it shows up once,
比如单词 a ，它只出现一次，
but you do it twice,
但你做了两次，
because something failed,
因为有些事情失败了，
and now you have a, 1 a, 1,
现在你得到了 a,1 a,1 ，
so your a count is going to be wrong.
所以你的 a 计数会是错的。
How, yeah, I'm confused.
怎么回事，是的，我很困惑。
Yes, right, how do they work,
是的，它们是怎么工作的，
it seems like if you don't do anything,
好像如果你什么都不做，
then this is really highly inconvenient,
那么这真的非常不方便，
where it actually returns to the application,
它返回到应用程序，
will compute the wrong result.
将计算错误的结果。
They said use checksums and a unique IDs to check,
他们说使用校验和和唯一的 ID 来检查，
you know every yeah, every record was like once.
每一条记录都只有一次。
Additionally, when you do record appends,
另外，当你做记录追加时，
the response which has returned from the primary to the client,
从 primary 返回给客户端的响应，
gives you the offset into the file,
为你提供文件的偏移量，
where your data was actually written,
你的数据实际写入的地方，
and the rest of it is assumed to be like undefined.
而其余的部分则被认为是未定义的。
Yeah, that I think the key point here correct is,
是的，我认为这里的关键点是，
like basically the application doesn't interact with the file system directly,
应用程序不直接与文件系统交互，
interact for some library,
是与某些库交互，
in the library,
在那个库里，
basically if you write append records,
如果你写入追加记录，
the library sticks an id in it,
那个库在绑定一个 id 给它，
and so and also use the library to read these records,
同时也使用那个库读取哪些记录，
and so if you see a record with the same id,
所以，如果你看到具有相同 id 的记录，
you know skip the second one,
可以跳过第二个，
because you know it's been clearly the same one.
因为你知道这显然是同一个。
And you know they have double, an extra thing in there for checksums
它们还有一个额外的东西，检查和，
to make sure the record didn't get garbled,
确保记录不会被篡改，
and basically to detect change in the bytes,
也为了检测字节的变化，
but you know the id basically helps them to decide,
id 会帮助他们做出决定，
allows the library to decide,
允许库来决定，
well, this is the same record,
好的，这是相同的记录，
I'm not gonna give it to the application,
我不会把它交给应用程序，
or the applications doesn't need to process it.
或者应用程序不需要处理它。
Okay?
好的?
My question is,
我的问题是，
instead of rewriting to every replica,
除了重写每个副本，
wouldn't it be better to remember which replica is failing,
记住哪个副本失败不是更好吗，
and to stop until it can be written to that one.
停止直到它可以被写入。
Yeah, there's a bunch of different designs possible,
是的，可能有很多不同的设计，
when let's return to later,
当我们稍后再回来，
you know I think one reason that they do this this way is,
我认为他们这样做的一个原因是，
like if a temporary failure,
如果是暂时的失败，
like a network disconnection or whatever you know the lease,
比如网络断开或租约问题，
the write will succeed and they will continue,
写入将会成功，它们可以继续，
and doesn't have to be any reconfiguration,
并且不需要做任何重新配置，
there has to be nothing you know
什么都不用做，
and the write can just keep going, right,
写入可以继续下去，
you know so the write doesn't have to fail.
所以，写入不是必须失败。
Okay.
好的。
It's just a quick question in general,
我有一个简短的问题，
the all of these servers are trusted, right, there's no.
所有这些服务器都是可信的，没有。
Yes, absolutely, this is actually important point,
是的，当然，这是重要的一点，
this is not like you know your Linux file system,
这不像 Linux 文件系统，
where there's permissions and access control writes
有权限和访问控制写入
and all that kind of stuff,
以及诸如此类的东西，
the servers are completely trusted,
服务器是完全可信的，
the clients are trusted, the masters trusted,
客户端是可信的， master 是可信的，
the software written by Google is trusted,
Google 写的软件是可信的，
the whole thing is trusted,
整个事情都是可信的，
right, this is your complete internal file system.
这是完全内部的文件系统。
In fact, it's sort of cool,
事实上，这很酷，
it's like a little bit may be surprising,
可能有点令人惊讶，
that we don't even know about this file system in such amout detail,
我们甚至不知道这个文件系统的这么多细节，
because it's only used inside Google,
因为它只在 Google 内部使用，
and one of the cool things is that,
其中一件很酷的事情是，
you know period of time and still they do,
有一段时间，他们仍然在这样做，
they wrote up the papers
他们撰写了论文，
and describing actually how these systems work,
并描述这些系统是如何工作的，
and there's one reason we know that,
我们知道这个只有一个原因，
it's actually extremely cool, that they did that.
他们这样做是非常酷的。
Okay.
好的。
So okay, so we now understand how read works, what write works,
好的，我们现在了解了读取是如何工作的，写入是如何工作的，
you know there's some sort of interesting behaviors,
有一些有趣的行为，
I want to talk a little bit more about consistency, correct,
我想更多地谈谈一致性，
and that really comes down to
这会归结为，
you know what a read observe after you did append,
在你追加之后，读取会观察到什么，
and the homework question really got after this,
家庭作业的问题会在这之后，
and what I would like to do now is
我现在想要做的是，
to take a quick break out, like five minutes,
简短休息一下，比如五分钟，
and so you can discuss you know the answer to this question,
所以你们可以讨论这个问题的答案，
and then come back
然后回来，
and talk a little bit more in detail about consistency.
更详细地讨论一下一致性。
Okay?
好的?
I'm gonna make Lily.
我要让 Lily （设置 zoom ）。
Okay, everybody back.
好了，大家回来了。
Can everybody here me, double checking.
大家能听到我吗，检查一下。
Yeah, hey, professor, question,
是的，教授，有一个问题，
can you go back to the slide with the,
你能够回到幻灯片，
when we talked about the write slide here,
当我们谈到写入时的幻灯片，
so you mentioned,
就像你提到的，
the master responds to the client through the version number,
master 通过版本号响应客户端，
and if that is the key,
如果这是关键，
then is it possible, is it even possible,
那有没有可能，
would even have to read like a stale data,
是否需要读取旧数据，
because the client has a version number
因为客户端具有版本号，
and the chunk servers without the version number,
而块服务器没有版本号，
so they can just compare those,
这样他们可以比较这些，
if they don't match the client,
如果它们与客户端不匹配，
the chunk servers can just say,
块服务器可以说，
I I have a stale data,
我有一个旧数据，
so you should not read this.
所以你不应该读取这个。
Okay, let's go,
好的，我们，
yeah, let's go for this scenario a little bit more detail.
是的，让我们来看一下这个场景的更多细节。
Let me actually zoom this window.
让我来放大这个窗口。
Okay, let's talk about it,
好的，我们来谈谈，
so I think this scenario we're talking about,
我认为我们正在讨论的这个场景，
that leads into a problematic situation as follows,
这会导致下面的问题，
we have primary, we have secondary,
我们有 primary ，我们 secondary ，
two secondary, secondary one, secondary two,
两个 secondary ， S1 S2 ，
we have a client at this side,
我们在这边有个客户端，
we have a primary,
我们有一个 primary ，
client reach you know it's back like a version number say 10,
客户端收到返回的版本号，比如是 10 ，
the, later on another primary will,
随后，另一个 primary 将会，
okay, so S2 get some servers,
好的，所以 S2 获得一些服务器，
then at some point, the,
然后在某个时候，
so this information is cached on the side,
这个信息被缓存在（客户端），
you know, maybe you know one of the secondary is like S2 crashes,
也许一个 secondary 比如 S2 崩溃，
or at least appears to be disconnected from the network,
或者至少与网络断开，
so what the master will do is increment version numbers,
所以 master 要做的是递增版本号，
you know go to 11 messages 11,
转到 11 ，消息 11 ，
then you know another client may come around and start writing,
然后，另一个客户端可能会过来，开始写入，
so we'll write a new value to S1 and S2 for the file,
所以，我们为该文件的 S1 和 S2 写入一个新值，
so the chunk has now been updated,
所以块现在已经更新了，
so let's say chunks original 10 same as version number,
我们假设原始版本号为 10 ，
now it's 11 here,
现在这里是 11 ，
but you know it's the case,
但是情况是这样的，
that even though the master primary secondary couldn't talk S2,
即使 master primary secondary 不能访问 S2 ，
but the second client,
但是第二个客户端，
first client could still talk to the secondary,
第一个客户端仍然与那个 secondary 交互，
and it will read the version numbers match,
它将读取到与之匹配的版本号，
they're both 10,
它们都是 10 ，
and it will read, it'll send 10 back, right,
它会发回 10 ，
so you have a case where the write has completed,
所以，你有一种情况，写入已经完成，
as acknowledged to be okay,
并确认已经成功，
and nevertheless,
尽管如此，
there's a client that actually will read a stale value back.
还是有一个客户端会读取一个旧的值。
So, why doesn't the 11 go back to the client?
那么，为什么 11 不回到客户端呢？
The first client,
第一个客户端，
the reason is because the first client caches it for a longer period of time,
原因是第一客户端将其缓存了更长的时间，
they don't actually have anything in the protocol that actually does that.
他们在协议中没有做到这个的内容。
So does the version increment,
当版本会更新，
when the, when the system tries to push an update to S2,
当系统尝试将更新推送到 S2 时，
and it's not able to, or.
还是不能，或者。
Version numbers only increment,
版本号递增只是在，
the version number is maintained by the master,
版本号由 master 维护的，
they only increment when you select a new primary,
它们只在选择新的 primary 时才会增加，
not when you do it,
当你这样做的时候不会，
there's a there's also a serial number, that they talk about,
他们还提到了一个序列号，
but its different from the version number,
但它与版本号不同，
that just to order you know the writes.
它是你写入的顺序。
Okay?
好的?
How does the primary know which secondary is it has to check with,
primary 如何知道它必须与哪个 secondary 进行检查，
before making, before completing it write successfully.
在完成写入之前。
The primary, the master tells it,
primary ， master 告诉它的，
master tells the primary you know secondary you need to update.
master 告诉 primary 你需要更新 secondary 。
So when the master basically issues the lease to the primary,
所以，当 master 向 primary 发出租约时，
and if one of the secondaries is down at that moment,
如果当时有一个 secondary 出了故障，
does the master consider this a failure,
master 是否认为这是一次失败，
or does it just update the version number for the servers that are alive,
或者它只是更新处于活动状态的服务器的版本号，
and it just forget about the other one,
而它只是忽略另一个，
because it's going to have an outdated version number anyway.
因为它无论如何都会有一个过时的版本号。
Yeah, the papers is a little bit [],
是的，论文有点[]，
exactly how the recovery part the reconfiguration stuff works,
恢复部分，重新配置是如何工作的，
but I imagine that,
但是我想，
basically the primary actually does heartbeats with P1 S1 S2,
primary 与 P1 S1 S2 之间有心跳，
in some point, the side you know S2 is dead,
在某个时刻， S2 挂掉了，
and at that point, it will point
在这个时刻，它将指向，
and the lease the primary maybe runs out,
primary 的租约可能会到期，
and then it will create a new primary and a new S1 and another S,
然后，它将创建一个新的 primary 和一个新的 S1 ，另一个 S ，
you know actual hold you know,
实际持有，
or maybe just S1,
或者可能只是 S1 ，
because there's no, no additional chunk server,
因为没有额外的块服务器，
and that forms the new replica group for that chunk.
这形成了这个块的新的副本组。
Also, the lease doesn't run out yet, basically.
此外，租约还没有到期。
Well, the primary we can't appoint,
好的， primary 不能指定，
okay so here's some interesting cases,
好的，这里有一些有趣的案例，
let's see,
我们看一下，
so, you guys are doing exactly the thing I want,
你们做的就是我想的，
based on this paper,
在这篇论文的基础上，
which you really start thinking about all the problematic cases.
你开始思考所有有问题的情况。
And this is exactly how you think about consistency,
这正是你对一致性的看法，
when you start thinking about consistency,
当你开始考虑一致性时，
you need to consider all possible failures,
你需要考虑所有可能的失败，
and argue whether you know those failures lead to inconsistencies.
并争论这些失败是否会导致不一致。
So, one thing let's talk about this one case,
所以，有一件事，我们来谈谈这个情况，
where we've got a master, we've got a primary,
我们有一个 master ，我们有一个 primary ，
and let's say the primary in the master get disconnected,
我们假设 primary 和 master 断开连接，
actually let me draw the picture slightly differently,
让我以稍微不同的方式来画这幅图，
master in the middle,
master 在中间，
and we got server, we got server here, you know S1, S2,
我们这里有服务器， S1 S2 ，
and let's say S2 is the primary,
假设 S2 是 primary ，
and so you know whatever you may talk to some other servers out there,
所以，你可能会与其他服务器交互，
perhaps S1 is the is one of the secondary for this primary.
也许 S1 是这个 primary 的一个 secondary 。
So let's say a network partition,
我们假设网络分裂，
so the master sends messages, you know heartbeat messages,
所以 master 发送心跳消息，
doesn't get a response,
没有得到响应，
when can the master point to a new primary.
什么时候 master 会指向新的 primary 。
When the lease is over for S2?
当 S2 的租约到期？
Yeah, right, because primary has to wait,
是的，因为 primary 必须等待，
the master has to wait until the lease has expired,
master 必须等待直到租约到期，
because if the lease was not expired,
因为如果租约没有到期，
then maybe we have two primaries at the same time, right,
那么我们可能会同时有两个 primary ，
P1 and P2 are staying at the same time,
P1 和 P2 同时存在，
and would that be bad?
那会不会很糟糕？
Yeah, then I think,
是的，然后我想，
wait, would would clients, clients wouldn't know where to send to,
客户端不知道发送到哪里，
and the master wouldn't know which one is primary, right.
master 也不知道哪一个是 primary 。
Well, presumably some clients still talking to this primary, right,
大概有些客户端还在跟这个 primary 交互，
while you might be talking to this primary,
同时你也可能与这个 primary 交互，
in a primary for the same chunk.
同一块的 primary 。
I think you get very bizarre ordering, right,
我觉得东西会很奇怪，
where like some writes will get lost,
一些写入操作会丢失，
you know you know it would be a mess.
那会是一团糟。
It would be not a principal,
它不会是一个[原则]，
you know argument where one,
争论哪里，
you know where all writes happening order and one at a time.
所有写入的顺序，一次写入一个。
So this is a bad situation,
所以这是一个糟糕的情况，
and this situation is avoided,
这种情况是可以避免的，
like the split-brain syndrome, is sometimes called split brain syndrome,
比如脑裂，有时被称为脑裂，
where you end up with a system where have two masters.
那里你最终会得到一个有两个 master 的系统。
And this is problem here avoided, because of the lease,
这里避免这个问题，因为使用了租约，
and the master will not appoint any other primary
master 不会指定任何其他 primary ，
until the lease of the first primary absolutely has has expired,
知道第一个 primary 的租约到期，
and it knows even if the primary is up,
它知道即使 primary 是运行的，
but not reachable to it,
但它无法达到，
but may be reasonable to other clients,
但对其他客户端来说可能是合理的，
that primary won't accept any write messages anymore,
那个 primary 将不再接受任何写入消息，
because lease has expired.
因为租约已经到期了。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Okay, let me say one more thing before wrapping up,
好的，在结束之前，让我再说一件事，
apologizes, partly because you know, I had some technical problems,
抱歉，因为我有一些技术问题，
but I wanted to make one more point,
但我想再说一个点，
and it came up in the discussion too in the breakout room,
这也是在分解会议室讨论中提出的，
which is you know how could you do better,
那就是如何才能做得更好，
how to get strong consistency,
如何获得强一致性，
or maybe just stronger,
或者只是变得更强，
got pretty strong consistency,
获得了相当强的一致性，
that you know not with some you know issues.
不是关于的问题。
And so there's a hundred different ways you could do it,
所以有很多不同的方法来做，
and in fact, you know, what we're going to be seeing.
事实上，我们将要看到的。
You know one, I think one issue that shows up here all the time is,
我认为这里经常出现的一个问题是，
like you could instead of like obtaining the primary and then reporting,
除了获得 primary 然后报告，
making writes visible incrementally,
以增量方式写入，
it's probably not a good idea,
这可能不是个好主意，
so you probably want to do is,
所以你可能想要做的是，
like update all secondary primaries or not,
更新所有 secondary primary 或者不更新，
but not in this you know particular design,
但不是在这个设计中，
where like somebody get updated and some may not get updated,
有些更新了，有些可能没有更新，
that's actually visible to the client.
这对客户端是可见的。
So there's a bunch of like you know techniques or protocol
所以有很多技术或协议
changes that you could do,
改变你可以做的，
that will make this better
会让它变得更好，
and in fact you will see in labs 2 and 3,
事实上，你将在实验 2 和 3 中看到，
you will build systems that actually have the stronger properties,
你将构建的系统具有更强的属性，
and deal with the scenarios you know concurrently lead to consistency.
处理并发的场景，从而实现一致性。
In fact, if you look at Google self,
事实上，如果你看看 Google 自己，
and we'll read some of these [] later,
我们之后会看到，
Google build additional storage systems,
Google 建造了更多的存储系统，
other storage systems that have stronger consistency,
其他一致性更强的存储系统，
and basically tailored those to a different application domain,
并且针对不同的应用领域做了定制，
for example, like in like halfway to term read the paper Spanner,
比如，在学期中看的 Spanner 论文，
you know that actually has a much stronger storage for consistency
它是具有更强大的一致性存储，
and and even have support for transactions.
甚至支持事务。
But it was like the application domain is quite different,
但应用程序领域是完全不同的，
you know you can sort of see here,
你可以在这里看到，
the GFS is really tailored,
GFS 是量身定制的，
you know to sort of running mapreduce jobs.
为了运行 mapreduce 作业。
Okay, so I hope this is a useful introduction for consistency,
好的，我希望这是一个关于一致性的有用的介绍，
and start thinking about these kinds of problems,
开始思考这类问题，
because they would be recurring set of problems,
因为它们会重复出现一系列问题，
that will show up in the rest of the term.
将在本学期余下的时间里体现出来。
And I apologize for running over a little bit.
很抱歉，超出一些时间。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Hang around, so people want to ask additional questions,
如果你们想问更多的问题，可以继续，
feel free to ask it,
请随意提问，
and if you have to run to another class,
如果你必须上另一节课，
you know please run to another class.
请去上另一节课。